Welcome, students,
to the Pharmacology
of Antihypertensive
Agents. This is the
first part in a three
-part video series.
We'll be talking about
the renin-angiotensin
system antagonists,
also known as the RAS
inhibitors, in this video.
Dr. Goldstein speaking.
Please contact me if you'd like
to chat about pharmacology.
Here are the learning
objectives. pharmacokinetics,
mechanisms,
mechanisms, mechanisms,
mechanisms of action,
mechanisms of adverse effects
and drug interactions,
and contraindications.
And you should be able
to select appropriate
antihypertensive agents,
especially for initial
therapy, and you should
be able to know how to
monitor the patient,
at least superficially.
Here are the preparation
materials. I highly recommend
the practice questions.
In fact, they're required.
It's the only thing,
for me, that's required.
I have offered you suggestions
on ways to help you
learn, on references that
you might find helpful,
especially if you prefer
them to watching the video.
Of course, my notes
handout, you don't have to
memorize, certainly,
but it's there with full
explanations to help
you understand things.
And you can do a
search of the handout
to find the answers
to the practice quiz.
Here are some more suggestions
to help you master a
topic to help you learn
rather than rote memorize.
And the next couple of
slides is pointing out
what you really need
to learn, how to focus
your learning so that
it's more efficient.
Prerequisites of pharmacology
learning, as with all
of pharmacology learning,
is to understand the
mechanisms and effects of the
therapeutic interventions.
And we do this by
understanding the physiology.
You must know the
physiology. First, the
pathophysiology in order
to understand how these
drugs are working,
what they're doing, and
why we are using them
for specific treatments.
And I'm not going to
read this slide to you.
I know you can do that
very well on your own.
A little background
about regulation of
blood pressure. All
antihypertensive drugs
produce effects by
interfering with normal
mechanisms of blood
pressure regulation.
Hence, you need to
understand the physiology.
Antihypertensive therapy
can induce compensatory
responses to a drop
in blood pressure,
increased sympathetic
outflow, increased
renin secretion. A
drop in blood pressure.
This figure shows very
simply the relationships
between these components
of blood pressure.
Antihypertensive agents
work by reducing peripheral
resistance, cardiac
output, and or volume.
The RAS inhibitors reduce
peripheral vascular
resistance and
potentially blood volume.
The RAS inhibitors work at
the resistance arterioles
and the capacitance vessels,
the venules actually.
Direct vasodilators
reduce peripheral vascular
resistance. It makes sense
because they're causing
vasodilation. And
sympatholytics, which are also
called sympathoplegics,
inhibit the cardiac
function and increase pooling
incapacitance vessels.
Diuretics depletes body
sodium, so natriuresis
and water diuresis, and
reduce blood volume. They
possibly have other
mechanisms of action as well.
Arterial pressure is
determined by cardiac output
and peripheral resistance,
the two together.
Cardiac output is determined by
stroke volume and heart rate.
Peripheral resistance is
determined by vascular
structure and function.
And we'll be talking about
effects of these drugs on
the arterioles particularly.
Regulation of
renin release. This
scheme shows the
different ways that
renin gets stimulated
to be secreted.
We see hypotension
or hypovolemia
causing renal hypoperfusion.
And that's the key,
the hypoperfusion.
and this type of
perfusion is sensed by
baroreceptors in the wall
of the affarin arterial
and that will stimulate
renin release by cardiac
and arterial baroreceptors
in circulating catecholamines
that stimulate sympathetic
tone and stimulate
beta-1 receptors in the
juxtaglomerular apparatus
of the kidney. And that
enhances renin secretion.
And a reduction in
the salt delivery
to the cells of
the macula densa
also enhances renin
secretion. And
renin release,
renin is an enzyme,
it causes formation of
angiotensin 1, which is
converted by angiotensin
converting enzyme to angiotensin
2. And angiotensin 2
will directly cause
vasoconstriction, stimulating
blood pressure, stimulating
systemic blood pressure.
And it will cause
aldosterone secretion, which
causes renal and sodium
reabsorption and extracellular
volume expansion.
Baroreflexes provide
rapid moment-to
-moment adjustments
in blood pressure.
And this scheme here
illustrates the mechanisms.
First of all, central
sympathetic neurons from the
vasomotor area of the
medulla are tonically active.
Carotid baroreceptor
stimulated by vessel wall
stretch inhibits central
sympathetic discharge.
The wall stretch
indicates a high pressure,
so central sympathetic
discharge is inhibited.
Baroreceptors that
sense reduction in
arterial pressure,
reduced wall stretch,
disinhibit sympathetic
discharge. And when
that happens, there is
a reflex increase in
sympathetic outflow,
which increases peripheral
vascular resistance,
and cardiac output.
And the kidney provides
long-term blood
pressure control by
controlling blood volume.
Question for you, how
does each of the following
systems contribute to
blood pressure regulation?
I suggest you might want
to turn off to pause
the video and think
about these things. So
I'll give you that chance.
Go ahead and pause.
Okay,
here are the answers.
And this is a review.
Physiologically, in both
normal and hypertensive
individuals, blood pressure
is maintained by moment-to
-moment regulation of cardiac
output and peripheral
vascular resistance exerted
at precapillary arterioles,
postcapillary venules,
and the heart.
The kidney contributes to
maintenance of blood pressure
by regulating the volume
of intravascular fluid.
The body responds to acute
changes in blood pressure
through the baroreceptors
located within blood vessels
by inhibiting or disinhibiting
sympathetic discharge.
Hormonal and volume
-related factors contribute
to the long-term
regulation of arterial
pressure and you might
want to pause the video
to look at these answers
since they've been
blocked off on your
copy of the PowerPoint.
Treatment of hypertension
goals, well lifestyle
modifications. First and
foremost, drug therapy.
As with all pharmacotherapy,
it should be individualized.
Therapy for the
individual patient.
Optimizing therapy for
the individual patient.
I'm just putting up
the 2017 ACC American
College of Cardiology
and AHA high blood
pressure guidelines.
There are others.
We'll just look
at these for now.
So normal is considered
less than 120
over 80 millimeters of
mercury. Elevated is
120 to 129 and
diastolic less than 80.
Stage 1 is considered
130 to 139 or
diastolic 80 to 89
millimeters of mercury.
Stage 2 is considered
systolic at least 140 or
diastolic at least 90
millimeters of mercury.
And we have hypertensive
crisis indicated here.
I'm not going to
be talking about
hypertensive crisis
in this lecture.
Screening for
cardiovascular disease
risk factors in adults
with hypertension
because smoking increases
the risk. Excessive
weight, diabetes, dyslipidemia,
low fitness, unhealthy
diet psychosocial stress
sleep apnea are all risk
factors for cardiovascular
disease and a hypertension
evaluation for target
organ damage established
cardiovascular or renal
disease cardiovascular
risk factors lifestyle
contributors and of course
drugs certain drugs can
cause elevations in blood
pressure and I've listed
out a few of them here.
Sympathomimetics
makes sense NSAIDs
cause reabsorption
of sodium in water.
Drugs containing sodium
so many antibiotics
in intravenous form
are in sodium salts and
they're given frequently
many times a day and
And the sodium levels
can go up in the patient.
Erythropoietin increases
the viscosity of the blood.
Angiogenesis inhibitors
also increase the risk.
Integrating osteopathic
principles and practice and
OMT in patient care. And this
includes pharmacotherapy.
So here is a question. I
invite you to pause your video.
A 42-year-old person presents
with new-onset hypertension.
What areas might you
examine for viscerosomatic
reflexes to help you decide
if this patient's issue
is primary hypertension
or secondary hypertension?
And I thank the
NYITCOM OMM faculty
for helping me out with this.
The answer is
Chapman reflexes or
viscerosomatic reflexes
to adrenals and kidneys.
So let's delve into
the pharmacology now.
Here's a list of the
agents that we're
going to be covering
in the three lectures.
So part one is the
ACE inhibitors,
angiotensin receptor blockers,
and the direct
renin inhibitors.
The preferred
initial therapy, and
this comes from the guidelines,
are the angiotensin
converting enzyme inhibitors,
angiotensin 2, AT1
receptor blockers,
calcium channel blockers,
the long-acting,
thiazide type or
thiazide-like diuretics.
And other options, should a
patient need additional therapy
in order to reduce the
blood pressure, to achieve
the blood pressure
goals, are beta blockers,
beta adrenergic receptor
blockers, alpha-adrenergic
receptor blockers, alpha
-2 agonists, vasodilators,
and direct renin
inhibitor. So please notice
that the ACE inhibitors
and ARBs are preferred.
The direct renin inhibitor
is not preferred.
This is guideline information.
The attained blood pressure
is the major outcome
determinant of reduction
of cardiovascular risk.
That's the whole point of
doing this. It's not the
choice of drug. Therapy
should be patient-specific.
But the guidelines are
very helpful in providing
information on the
preferred agents. And
this is related to the
outcome, determinants
and reduction of
cardiovascular risk, The
ease of taking them,
long-acting, for example,
and two drug pills
or three drug single
pills taken once daily
are certainly better
for improved adherence
to the therapy.
And, of course, we have to
remember the side effects.
So drugs that have a
favorable side effect profile.
So efficacy,
favorable side effect
profile, and ease of use.
Monotherapy recommendations for
people with stage
1 hypertension.
An ACE inhibitor, an
ARB, or a calcium channel
blocker. And if the
patient will benefit from
diuresis, then a thiazide
or thiazide-like diuretic,
so patients with edema,
possibly osteoporosis,
possibly patients with
calcium nephrolithiasis.
Now, most patients are going to
require two-drug
therapy to begin with.
and we see combination
therapy used in these
categories and this
these differ by expert
but they're pretty
much the same point
which is to reduce the
cardiovascular risk
recommendations are either
an ACE or an ARB never both
plus a calcium channel
blocker and this is related
to findings in the ACCOMPLISH
trial that showed this
combination was more
efficacious than the ACE or ARB
combination with a thiazide
or thiazide-like diuretic.
But still, that said, the
combination including a
thiazide is certainly efficacious
in reducing cardiovascular
risk. And another option
is a calcium channel
blocker with a thiazide or
a thiazide-like diuretic.
So now the RAS inhibitors.
Angiotensin-converting
enzyme inhibitors and ARBs
we'll be looking at together.
Just a quick review of
where they're acting.
The angiotensin-converting
enzyme inhibitors act at
this point. inhibiting
conversion to angiotensin 2.
They also inhibit the
conversion of bradykinin. Not on
here is they inhibit the
conversion of substance P.
I should say they inhibit the
activation of these peptides.
And these are vasodilating
peptides. So ACE inhibitors
increase levels of
bradykinin and substance P.
Now our angiotensin receptor
blockers act at this point.
So further downstream,
angiotensin 2 is
formed, but the block is
here. Now you'll notice
that these drugs, ARBs,
do not block here.
So, by blocking the
AT1 receptor, among
other functions, it
inhibits the release
of angiotensin 2
-induced aldosterone.
Angiotensin 2 has
so, so many effects.
Effects on peripheral
resistance, causing an
acute pressor response.
effects on renal
function, causing a
delayed pressor response,
and cardiovascular
structure, cardiovascular,
cardiac, and
vascular remodeling.
This figure sets out all
of the different effects
that angiotensin 2 has, and
therefore, these are the
effects that are going to
be blocked when we prevent
the actions of angiotensin
2 either by preventing
its synthesis or by
blocking its action at AT1.
I invite you to give
this scheme a good look.
It will really help you
understand the effects
of angiotensin 2 and
the blocking effects.
as it's stated in this figure
from Goodman and Gilman,
major physiologic effects
of angiotensin II.
Angiotensin II exerts
physiologic and
pathologic effects
on both the renal and
cardiovascular systems,
providing a rationale for
the therapeutic benefits
of RAS inhibition.
And
this scheme, it shows you
by looking at the various
organs, what's going on,
hopefully it'll help you.
I recommend that without
looking, after you've
given it some study, you
draw out your own schemes.
Now the receptors,
AT1 and AT2 receptors.
AT1 receptors are the
GQ type of protein
-coupled receptors. So they
increase cytosolic
calcium, stimulate PKC.
This causes
vasoconstriction. It's
responsible for the
hypertrophy that's seen,
fibrosis, inflammation,
nephropathy.
This is not the only type
of AT1 receptors, as we
can imagine, because
angiotensin 2 just has so many
different actions. There
are other GPCR types, and
the AT1 receptors are
subject to down-regulation.
So this is that regulatory
mechanism we talked
about in the Foundations
course in pharmacodynamics.
AT2 receptors are
the GI PCR types.
they cause vasodilation,
natrioresis, and
they antagonize gross
effects. So you can
see that it's
essentially the opposite.
Of course, that's
not all there is to
the story. There are
non-g-protein coupled
receptor pathways
that are involved,
and other types of
receptors are involved in
mediating the effects of
other types of angiotensin.
So ARBs block here,
ACE inhibitors
block here, because
angiotensin II is
not synthesized.
This scheme just shows
where the various drugs
interfere with the renin
-angiotensin-aldosterone
system. We have our
direct renin inhibitor.
We have our ACE inhibitors.
We have our ARBs.
And let's not forget our
mineralocorticoid
receptor antagonists.
Those were covered in
the diuretic selector.
So these are the ones we're
going to be talking about.
Here are all of the
drugs in the two classes.
As you can see, there
are only three stars.
Captopril is the prototype
of the ACE inhibitors.
Losartan is the prototype
of the angiotensin receptor
blockers. I've also included
enalapril because there's
another feature I'll show
you on the next slide.
Most ACE inhibitors are
small ester-containing
peptide prodrugs, hydrolyzed
by hepatic esterases
or intestinal esterases
to the active molecule.
There are two that are
active as the parent drug,
but all of the rest are
pro-drugs converted to
a much more potent
form, a much more potent
metabolite. And you see
that they all end in AT.
Enalaprilate, vicinaprilate,
benazaprilate,
moexaprilate, etc.
on down the line.
The active metabolites are
much more potent than the
ACE inhibitors, as I said,
than the parent compounds,
but the active molecules
have really poor
bioavailability, which is
why the pro-drugs are given.
The angiotensin receptor
blockers, on the other
hand, are just small
molecule non-peptide drugs.
General class pharmacokinetic
properties. This is
really enough for you to
be learning at this moment
because when you're going
to be looking at the
individual drugs for your
individual patient, you might
want to look up the
pharmacokinetics to get an idea
about them. But in general,
they're all oral, ACEs
and ARBs, with one exception
at the current time.
Enalaprilate is available
in an intravenous form.
So that's one reason why
I put enalaprilate here.
The other reason is that
captopril has to be given
two to three times a day.
and we know we would really
rather use long-acting
drugs especially if they
can be two drugs in a single
pill so all of the others
may be given once daily
for hypertension management
of the ACE inhibitors
and the ARBs all of them
can be given once daily
for hypertension management
uh what else do i want to
point out um really not
much very varying systemic
sorry varying serum half
-lives uh we need to remember
with most of them the
half-life will be longer
in the elderly patient of
some urinary excretion
some out only through the
feces some require dosage
adjustments, some don't.
Some go out through
the kidney as is,
not changed. Some are
further metabolized,
moderate to extensive
protein binding,
etc.
So the big takeaways ways,
I would say,
is they're oral,
enalaprilate is
intravenous, ARBs don't have
intravenous drugs,
captopril needs to be taken
two to three times a
day, and also on an empty
stomach, which I'm not
asking you to remember.
All of the rest
can be taken once
a day for hypertension
management.
ACE inhibitors are
competitive inhibitors of
angiotensin-converting
enzyme. They inhibit the
conversion of angiotensin 1
to 2. They reduce angiotensin
2 effects at both
AT1 and AT2 receptors
naturally because the
angiotensin 2 levels are down.
They do inhibit the degradation
of bradykinin and substance P.
Both of these are vasodilators.
Bradykinin is a vasodilating
peptide. Substance
P is a neuropeptide
and a neurotransmitter.
ARBs are competitive
antagonists of angiotensin
2 AT1 receptors with
very high affinity
binding they permit
activation of AT2 receptors
because they don't bind
to them and by inhibiting
AT1 receptor activity
they in turn stimulate
renin release which
increases circulating
angiotensin 2 levels, but
ARBs block the angiotensin
2 effects at AT1 receptors,
but not at AT2 receptors.
Let's take a look at the
effects, and this is of
both the ACE inhibitors
and the ARBs. They decrease
arterial and venous pressure
and peripheral vascular
resistance, which reduces
preload and afterload.
The heart rate and
cardiac output really
change very little
despite the decrease
in peripheral
vascular resistance.
And it is thought that the
reason is a resetting of
the baroreceptor reflex to
a lower arterial pressure.
Angiotensin 2 does affect
the baroreceptor reflex
and we are inhibiting
that angiotensin 2 effect.
They increase natrioresis
by increasing renal blood
flow and they also reduce
aldosterone secretion and
vasopressin secretion,
antidiuretic hormone secretion.
They decrease resistance
in the efferent glomerular
arteriole, which decreases
glomerular capillary pressure,
and decreases proteinuria.
And there you have the
rationale for their use
in chronic kidney disease.
And they prevent remodeling of
smooth muscle and
cardiac myocytes.
Now, the ARBs were
developed thinking that they
would be more effective
than the ACE inhibitors
because they're
acting directly on AT1
receptors, but they're not
inhibiting AT2 receptors.
Well, it turns out they
all seem to provide
similar benefits in
patients with hypertension,
heart failure, and
chronic kidney disease.
so they're really used more
or less interchangeably
at this point all of
the ACE inhibitors have
similar efficacy to each
other and the ARBs have
efficacy comparable to the
ACE inhibitors efficacy
of all of these drugs is
enhanced by concomitant
diuretic therapy and reduced
dietary sodium intake
hypertension Hypotension,
the ACE and ARBs are
included in the guidelines as
preferred initial therapy
option. They can be used alone
or in combination with other
antihypertensive agents.
Start low,
start low,
because they can
cause hypotension.
And this is especially
predominant with the first dose
or the first few doses.
So there is this potential
for a large initial drop in
blood pressure, especially
if the patient has an active
renin-angiotensin-aldosterone
system, as in patients
with volume contraction,
hypovolemia,
congestive heart failure,
and other situations in
which the renin-angiotensin
-aldosterone system is
supporting the patient's
blood pressure. So we're
blocking a renin-angiotensin
system with these drugs,
and boom, that blood
pressure can take a nosedive.
Lower blood pressure
to some extent
in most patients
with hypertension.
Most patients with
hypertension are going
to end up on combination
therapy, whether
it's two drugs or
three drugs or more.
The full effect
occurs after several
weeks, and this is
true with nearly
all of the
antihypertensive agents.
There is also seen
left ventricular
hypertrophy regression
with the ACE inhibitors
and ARBs and some
of the other drugs.
But this is not all
they're used for. Post
-myocardial infarction,
there have been beneficial
effects on mortality
seen in randomized
controlled clinical trials
in patients who have
had an acute myocardial
infarction, especially
an ST-elevation acute
myocardial infarction.
They induce sustained
blood pressure lowering,
regression of ventricular
hypertrophy. They
prevent ventricular
remodeling after myocardial
infarction, and other
mechanisms are likely.
Patients with heart failure
with reduced ejection
fraction. They've been
shown to improve symptoms,
reduce hospitalizations,
and prolong survival.
They are used with a
beta blocker, and if
the patient needs fluid
control, they're used
with a loop diuretic.
ACE inhibitors, ARBs,
or a naprilicin-ARB
combination, there's
only one on the
market at the moment,
Secubitril-Valsartan.
Naprilicin increases
the availability of
natriuretic peptides,
abridokinin, and substance
P, and these have
natriuretic vasodilatory
and antiproliferative
properties of their own.
So that's the reason
for the combination.
Of course, they're
not used as the
only treatment
of heart failure.
Proteinuric chronic
kidney disease, either
diabetic chronic kidney
disease or non-diabetic
chronic kidney disease,
they've been shown to
slow the progression of
the disease. They reduce
glomerular pressure,
one, by reducing blood
pressure, and all
antihypertensives do that.
These drugs also cause
dilation of the efferent
arterioles, which reduces
the pressure within the
glomerulus, and they
reduce protein excretion.
And they may have
other mechanisms
within the kidney as well.
adverse effects now hypotension
i've referred to that
a couple of times usually
occurs within the first few
doses most often observed
in patients who are in a
rast dependent state such
as volume depleted patients
patients i mean they reduce
the gfr why because they're
relaxing the efferent
arteriole and this is generally
not dangerous in a patient
who's not at otherwise
risk it's usually a modest
effect however in patients
whose renal perfusion is
already a problem it's already
severe and that perfusion
pressure is reduced further
by dilating the efferent
arteriole that can cause a
Acute Kidney Injury.
Of course, that has an acronym.
And hyperkalemia.
I should put a bunch of
exclamation points here.
ACE inhibitors and ARBs
reduce aldosterone secretion.
Aldosterone is responsible
for reabsorption
of sodium and excretion
of potassium in the
urine. And now we're
inhibiting that, so potassium
can be reabsorbed,
causing hyperkalemia.
More adverse effects.
The dry cough, it's not
dangerous, it's annoying,
it's bothersome. This
occurs in up to 20%
of patients, and it is
believed that it's the
result of accumulation of
bretokinin in substance P
and likely prostaglandins
in the lungs, causing
this irritation.
There is a low
incidence of dry cough
with angiotensin
receptor blocker
therapy, not zero,
but a low incidence.
angioedema is especially
related to the ACE
inhibitors it's rare fortunately
it's potentially fatal
but think about it 0.7
percent think about all
the millions and millions
and millions of patients
who take ACE inhibitors
it's still a it's still
a lot of patients who
can develop angioedema.
Again, it seems
the bradykinin and
substance P are
likely to be involved.
These are pro-inflammatory
peptides, and the
dilation, the vasodilation,
will cause this
vessel edema.
The incidence rates with
the ARBs are not higher
than with the non-RES
antihypertensive drugs. This is
from a later study that
demonstrated this effect.
Now, Omisartan, this is
a drug-specific, unique
adverse effect of
enteropathy characterized
by severe chronic
diarrhea and weight loss.
So here we have pictures of
angioedema in
different individuals.
Do not give to the
pregnant patient period
the end contraindicated
in all trimesters.
They can cause fetal
hypotension, and urea, renal
function depression, which
leads to oligohydramnios,
fetal lung hypoplasia,
skeletal malformation,
skull hypoplasia,
and even death.
And that's true with
all RAS inhibitors.
uh drug interactions well
we do not give ACEs and ARBs
together we do not give
ACE or ARB together with a
direct renal inhibitor we do
not combine RAS inhibitors
this is associated
with potentially life
-threatening adverse
effects hypotension syncope
hyperkalemia kidney
dysfunction and on top of it it
does not improve benefit
to put them together other
potassium sparing drugs
well these drugs already are
potassium sparing as it
were they cause reabsorption
of potassium so adding
an enac inhibitor or a
mineralocorticoid receptor
antagonist or an NSAID will further
increase the risk of
hyperkalemia and NSAIDs blunt
the antihypertensive effects
of the RAS inhibitors.
Now,
NSAIDs are available over
the counter. People treat
themselves. People may not
be aware of the potential
adverse effects that can
result from this drug
interaction. It's very,
very important to counsel
a patient, not once, but
every time they're seen.
and lithium levels may
increase so that requires
monitoring and possibly
adjustment of the lithium
dose let's take a look
now at the direct renin
inhibitor there's only one
at the moment alliscarine
and that's what it does it
just gets into this enzyme
renin and it blocks the
angiotensinogen from accessing
the catalytic site as a
result angiotensin 1 is not
formed and if angiotensin
1 is not formed therefore
angiotensin 2 won't be formed
and on down the line uh
this is a small molecule
drug oral it is a p
-glycoprotein substrate look
at this bioavailability.
It's only 3%. So remember,
P-glycoprotein is located
in the intestine, so it's
going to push the drug
out, and any drug that
gets into the liver can
be pushed into the biliary
system via P-glycoprotein,
and that is certainly
going to cause the vast
majority of the drug to
be excreted and not reach
the systemic circulation
what is the metabolism
interestingly
that's really hasn't
been defined it
might involve cyp3a4
it is excreted unchanged
in the feces via the
biliary system and also
whatever didn't get
absorbed it's got a long
half-life whatever actually
does get in which allows
once daily dosing.
Some of this drug, a small
percentage of whatever
gets in, is actually
excreted in the urine.
Now, patients who have a
low creatinine clearance
have an increased risk of
hyperkalemia. Why? Because
there's going to be more
drug in the bloodstream.
Progressive renal impairment
may also occur, and the
area under the concentration
versus time curve is
increased in patients who
are 65 and older. So we must
be very careful with dosing
if this drug is selected.
It is a highly potent selective
competitive inhibitor of renin.
Dose-dependent decreases
in angiotensin 1, 2,
aldosterone, naturally. It
decreases blood pressure,
as we would expect.
So how does it compare
to the other antihypertensive
drugs? Well, it's
comparable to the other
RAS inhibitors and to
the other types of
antihypertensive drugs in
terms of its ability to
lower the blood pressure.
The adverse effects,
hypotension, hyperkalemia,
nephrotoxicity,
cough, angioedema,
pregnancy contraindication,
and whatever else
angiotensin converting
enzyme inhibitors have.
What is it used for?
Hypertension only.
It is an alternative
treatment. It can be used as
monotherapy, but if an
ACE inhibitor or an ARB
is tolerable by the patient,
not contraindicated,
Certainly, those would
be the preferred agents.
Potentially significant
interactions may exist
requiring dose or frequency
adjustment, additional
monitoring, and or
selection of an alternative
agent. So we talked
about P-glycoprotein.
Strong P-glycoprotein
inducers or inhibitors can
affect alloscurin
systemic levels. And I put
down three strong P
-glycoprotein inhibitors that
should not be given
together with alloscarin,
etraconazole antifungals,
cyclosporine,
immunosuppressant, and
ritonavir, which is a CYP3A4
strong inhibitor and a
P-glycoprotein strong
inhibitor. All of these
are strong P-glycoprotein
inhibitors. Ritonavir is
also present in the COVID
drug Paxlovid, as
well as in many of the
protease inhibitors used
for the treatment of HIV.
And, of course, I know
I've said it, I don't know
how many times now, we don't
combine RAS inhibitors.
So I have a question here, and
you may want to
pause the video.
A 58-year-old non-diabetic
person presenting with
crushing chest pain is ultimately
diagnosed with acute ST
-elevation myocardial infarction
with anterior infarct.
Percutaneous coronary
intervention is performed. Post
-procedure oral pharmacotherapy
initiated prior to
discharge which consists of
low-dose aspirin, clopidogrel,
metoprolol or
metoprolol, succinate,
rosuvastatin, and low
-dose lisinopril. Pril,
pril, pril, you know
it's an ACE inhibitor.
Blood pressure is
carefully monitored.
The patient is at
high risk for what
RAS inhibitor-related
adverse effect?
I invite you to pause and
think about the answer.
Hypotension. First dose
hypotension can be marked in
patients with high RAS
activity or volume depletion.
Or there is high RAS
activity in volume depletion.
RAS activity is high due
to hemodynamic changes in
the period following an
acute myocardial infarction.
Evidence from randomized
trials with either
an ACE inhibitor or
ARB compared to placebo
demonstrates an
improvement in mortality.
and you may want to pause
the video for this question
the randomized double
-blind alliscarine trial and
type 2 diabetes using
cardiorenal endpoints also known
as altitude assigned 8
,561 patients to either
alliscarine or placebo as an
adjunct to the patient's ace
inhibitor or ARB therapy.
The primary endpoint was
a composite of the time
to cardiovascular death or
first occurrence of cardiac
arrest with resuscitation,
non-fatal myocardial
infarction, non-fatal stroke,
unplanned hospitalization
for heart failure,
end-stage renal disease, death
attributable to kidney failure,
need for renal
replacement therapy with
no dialysis or
transplantation available
or doubling of baseline
serum creatinine.
The trial was stopped early
after the second interim
analysis showing that
the addition of alaskarin
to standard therapy with
RAS blockade in patients
with type 2 diabetes at
high risk for cardiovascular
and renal events is not
supported by the data.
There was no benefit and
it might even be harmful.
Thinking about the
mechanism related adverse
effects of RAS inhibition,
particularly when RAS
inhibitors are combined,
what were two toxicities
occurring at a significantly
higher rate in the
alloscarin group compared
to the placebo group?
And what I'm asking you
to do is see if you can
anticipate what they were
based on your knowledge.
So I invite you to pause the
computer and think about it.
hypotension and
hyperkalemia, as well as
non-significantly
higher rate of other
adverse events, including
non-fatal stroke.
So in summary,
here is a scheme showing
the points at which
antihypertensive drugs are
acting to reduce blood pressure.
And I've circled where our
RAS inhibitors are working.
So RAS inhibitors reduce
peripheral vascular
resistance without reflex
sympathetic activation
and they decrease
aldosterone secretion.
ACE inhibitors increase
vasodilating peptides,
bradycarnin, and substance
B levels, which may also
be associated with causing
cough and angioedema.
Angiotensin receptor
blockers are associated
with lower incidence of
cough and angioedema.
Direct renin inhibitors can
cause these adverse effects.
ACE inhibitors and ARBs are
effective and widely used
in the treatment of hypertension,
post-acute myocardial
infarction therapy, heart
failure with reduced ejection
fraction, and proteinuric
chronic kidney disease.
Alaskarin is an option
for the management of
hypertension. It is not a
recommended first-line therapy.
RAS inhibitors
are generally well
-tolerated. They can cause
hypotension, especially
in people with
high RAS activity.
Other adverse effects
include modest
reduction in glomerular
filtration rate,
hyperkalemia, and
nephrotoxicity.
And this modest reduction
in GFR, please remember,
in the patient who is not
at risk is not a problem.
However, in patients who
already have reduced GFR,
these drugs can lead to acute
kidney injury, nephrotoxicity.
ACE inhibitors are
associated with a dry cough
and angioedema that may
be related to levels of
bretokinin and substance
P, which I said before.
Olmosartin is associated
with sprue-like enteropathy,
severe diarrhea, and weight
loss. Combinations of RAS
inhibitors should be avoided
due to increased risk
of hypotension, syncope, renal
impairment, and hyperkalemia.
RAS inhibitors are
contraindicated during pregnancy
because of the risk of
fetal hypotension, anuria,
and renal failure leading
to oligohydramnios. Fetal
malformations and death may
occur. And that concludes
part one of the lectures
on antihypertensive agents.
Thank you.